<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog</id>
    <title>Carrie Miyoshi Macfarlane Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-10-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Carrie Miyoshi Macfarlane Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/img/avatar200px-transparent.png</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Love Research]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/whyresearch</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/whyresearch"/>
        <updated>2024-10-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve come a long way! One of the first things I did when I became interested in technical writing was research. I found a great book, The Insider’s Guide to Technical Writing by Krista Van Laan, and I read it every day during my commute to the library. I filled it with bright green post-it notes to remind me of key points when I got my first job. Recently, one of those post-it notes helped me strengthen a relationship with a valued colleague.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve come a long way! One of the first things I did when I became interested in technical writing was research. I found a great book, <em>The Insider’s Guide to Technical Writing</em> by Krista Van Laan, and I read it every day during my commute to the library. I filled it with bright green post-it notes to remind me of key points when I got my first job. Recently, one of those post-it notes helped me strengthen a relationship with a valued colleague.</p>
<p>Most of my current employer's documentation was written by a colleague who has been with the company for more than a decade. We meet from time-to-time, but we work in different collections. Recently, we’ve started to review one another’s work.</p>
<p>We needed to set clear expectations for what we would and wouldn’t correct during review, so I proposed that we adopt a pre-publication checklist. I had created a checklist for the collection that I work in, so I suggested we use that as a foundation. I asked my colleague to take a look and suggest any changes. He said he liked the checklist quite a bit! It conformed to his style conventions and met his needs.</p>
<p>My colleague asked out of curiosity how I’d developed the checklist. I used many sources, but the backbone of the checklist came directly from a post-it I had affixed to one of the pages of Krista Van Laan’s book. Van Laan said that the best documentation is accurate, complete, error-free, and usable. I had recorded those priorities on a post-it, and I adopted them as the 4 main goals of the checklist.</p>
<p><em>The Insider's Guide to Technical Writing</em> made me feel so excited to become a tech writer! It’s fun to reminisce about that time of exploration, and it’s rewarding to see the results of my research.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/whyresearch#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Pre-publication checklist</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="question">Question<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/whyresearch#question" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Question" title="Direct link to Question">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>My colleague asked how I developed the checklist</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answer">Answer<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/whyresearch#answer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answer" title="Direct link to Answer">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>I used many sources, but the foundation of the checklist is <em>The Insider's Guide to Technical Writing</em></li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/whyresearch#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-insider-s-guide-to-technical-writing-krista-van-laan/18378904?ean=9781937434786" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>The Insider's Guide to Technical Writing</em> | by Krista Van Laan</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="workflow" term="workflow"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taxonomy]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/taxonomy</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/taxonomy"/>
        <updated>2024-09-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[My colleagues and I were having trouble communicating with one another. People were using different names for the same user interface (UI) elements. It would be an enormous undertaking to change communication habits across an organization, but one achievable first step we could take, I figured, would be to change terminology in written documents.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My colleagues and I were having trouble communicating with one another. People were using different names for the same user interface (UI) elements. It would be an enormous undertaking to change communication habits across an organization, but one achievable first step we could take, I figured, would be to change terminology in written documents.</p>
<p>So I decided to create a visual glossary of UI elements. The glossary would make it easy for writers to consistently use a single name for any given window or form. Because some UI elements aren’t labeled, I also would need to provide instructions on how to name UI elements. If we needed to refer to an unlabeled UI element, I could assign a name to it based on the rules in the naming guide. At the core of this naming guide was a hierarchy of color-coded categories and examples. I wanted to call the hierarchy a taxonomy.</p>
<p>But <em>was</em> it a taxonomy? I knew the term from librarianship. Librarians in my field used taxonomies to assign metadata in digital repositories. I’d seen the term occasionally in tech comm publications, but I hadn’t paid much attention to it. Now I wondered, do technical communicators use the term <em>taxonomy</em> in the same way that librarians do? It would be counterproductive (and ironic!) if I misused a term in my naming guide.</p>
<p>How do technical communicators use the term <em>taxonomy</em>? I did a little research. I found a great article that led me to a great webinar. And a book! (See below.) I learned that in technical communication <em>and</em> librarianship, a taxonomy is a system that facilitates categorization of information. It uses tools including hierarchies and controlled vocabulary to help people derive meaning from things like names, tags, headings, and labels. I called the hierarchy in my naming guide a taxonomy.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/taxonomy#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Naming Guide for UI Elements</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="questions">Questions<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/taxonomy#questions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Questions" title="Direct link to Questions">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Librarians would call a hierarchy of color-coded categories a <em>taxonomy</em>. Would technical communicators call it a taxonomy, too?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/taxonomy#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Yes! In tech comm <em>and</em> librarianship, a taxonomy is a system that facilitates categorization of information.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/taxonomy#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://review.content-science.com/what-is-a-taxonomy-for-content/#:~:text=A%20system%20for%20organizing%20content,(driving%20attribute%20%2B%20tag%20terminology)" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">What Is a Taxonomy for Content? | Content Science Review</a></li>
<li><a href="https://content-science.com/publications/content-advantage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>The Content Advantage</em> | by Colleen Jones</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="communication" term="communication"/>
        <category label="info architecture" term="info architecture"/>
        <category label="UI" term="UI"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Examples]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/examples</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/examples"/>
        <updated>2024-08-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back during my first few months as a tech writer, I was working on documentation for complicated software that’s used in an industry I knew nothing about. I felt like a blindfolded tour guide. If you’re a tech writer, you’ve probably felt like this sometimes, too! You can find your way to walls and then doors, but you can’t bring people to the rooms they want to go to. Ultimately, it was my experience as a librarian that helped me navigate.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back during my first few months as a tech writer, I was working on documentation for complicated software that’s used in an industry I knew nothing about. I felt like a blindfolded tour guide. If you’re a tech writer, you’ve probably felt like this sometimes, too! You can find your way to walls and then doors, but you can’t bring people to the rooms they want to go to. Ultimately, it was my experience as a librarian that helped me navigate.</p>
<p>After an interview with a subject matter expert and some experimentation, I'd learned enough to write accurate instructions. But as a former librarian who has led thousands of training sessions, I thought the instructions for the most complicated functions would be easier to understand if they were accompanied by examples. Since I wasn’t familiar with the industry, though, if I was going to provide realistic examples, I’d need to do more research.</p>
<p>I didn’t want to disappoint my new colleagues by taking too long. And I really didn’t want to place an unnecessary burden on my subject matter expert. I wondered if I should consider the job done. At this point, the blindfold was off: I could guide readers to the essential places, I just couldn’t explain very well why they’d want to go there.</p>
<p>Would it be worth the time it took to identify and write realistic examples? I did a little research and confirmed what I already knew to be true: concrete examples are useful in documentation, too.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/examples#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Documentation for software that's used in an industry that was unfamiliar to me</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="questions">Questions<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/examples#questions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Questions" title="Direct link to Questions">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Writing realistic examples for documentation takes a while when you don’t know the industry. Is it worth the time?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/examples#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Yes! Examples are essential for library training sessions, and they're essential for documentation too.</li>
<li>In fact, it’s a good idea to provide more than one example.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/examples#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.learningscientists.org/learning-scientists-podcast/2018/1/3/episode-10-concrete-examples" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Episode 10 - Concrete Examples | The Learning Scientists</a> (If you don’t have time to listen, read the show notes! They’re just as good.)</li>
<li><a href="https://blog.thinkst.com/2023/08/default-behaviour-sticks-and-so-do-examples.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Default Behaviour Sticks (And So Do Examples) | Thinkst</a>]</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="communication" term="communication"/>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seven, Plus or Minus Two]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/seven-plus-or-minus</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/seven-plus-or-minus"/>
        <updated>2024-07-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[When I review draft knowledgebase articles for publication, I provide feedback and explanations that I extract from our style guide. My hope is that if the author understands why I’ve made a suggestion, they’ll make the change on their own next time. Sometimes, I double-check to make sure the rationale in our style guide is still valid.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I review draft knowledgebase articles for publication, I provide feedback and explanations that I extract from our style guide. My hope is that if the author understands why I’ve made a suggestion, they’ll make the change on their own next time. Sometimes, I double-check to make sure the rationale in our style guide is still valid.</p>
<p>Recently, when I double-checked a style convention that I had long thought to be true, I found a bit of controversy. I had been taught that lists with more than 7-10 steps should be divided into sections with subheadings. Because cognitive psychology research showed that people can remember about 7 chunks of information at a time, many web designers concluded that menus should contain no more than 7 items, plus or minus 2. This “Seven, Plus or Minus Two” convention made sense in technical writing, too: excessively long to-do lists are overwhelming.</p>
<p>However, it now seems that web designers took cognitive research too far. The research was about memory, not reading. Yes, people can remember about 7 chunks of information, but they can <em>read</em> more than that!</p>
<p>What does this discovery mean for our style guide? Understanding the finer points of this convention will help me provide informed feedback, but I’m not going to change the guide. Even refutations of the 7 plus or minus 2 rule still say that structure and hierarchy are essential. Breaking a long list into sections with subheadings remains a best practice.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/seven-plus-or-minus#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Advice about ordered and unordered lists</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="question">Question<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/seven-plus-or-minus#question" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Question" title="Direct link to Question">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>How many items in a list is too many items?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/seven-plus-or-minus#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Lists should contain no more than 7-10 items</li>
<li>If a list contains more than 7-10 items, divide the list into sections with headings</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/seven-plus-or-minus#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://uxmyths.com/post/931925744/myth-23-choices-should-always-be-limited-to-seven" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Myth #23: Choices should always be limited to 7+/-2 | UX Myths</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/chunking/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How Chunking Helps Content Processing | Nielsen Norman Group</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.britannica.com/biography/George-A-Miller#ref1200615" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">George A. Miller | American Psychologist &amp; Cognitive Scientist | Britannica</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
        <category label="info architecture" term="info architecture"/>
        <category label="style guide" term="style guide"/>
        <category label="UI" term="UI"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Large Screenshots]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/large-screenshots</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/large-screenshots"/>
        <updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was reviewing a draft article for our knowledgebase when I realized that I needed to add advice about screenshots to our style guide. I’d nearly been lulled into complacency as I ticked off items in our pre-publication checklist. Yes, the scope statement was accurate; yes, the instructions were written as numbered steps; yes, large screenshots were annotated…]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was reviewing a draft article for our knowledgebase when I realized that I needed to add advice about screenshots to our style guide. I’d nearly been lulled into complacency as I ticked off items in our pre-publication checklist. Yes, the scope statement was accurate; yes, the instructions were written as numbered steps; yes, large screenshots were annotated…</p>
<p>Wait. Those screenshots were really large. I had to scroll to get past them! They were distracting. The screenshots added value, but they needed to be smaller.</p>
<p>I checked our style guide and confirmed it provided no advice about how much of a screen to include in a screenshot. I’d have to add advice, and I wanted to cite some research for people who were interested in learning more.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/large-screenshots#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Screenshots</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="question">Question<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/large-screenshots#question" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Question" title="Direct link to Question">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>How much of a screen should be captured in a screenshot?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/large-screenshots#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Include only the relevant parts of the screen, with enough context to reassure the reader that they're in the right place.</li>
<li>Cropping helps the reader focus on the information that you want to convey</li>
<li>Cropping can future-proof a screenshot in case other parts of the interface change.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/large-screenshots#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Bhatti, Jared, Zachary Sarah Corleissen, Jen Lambourne, David Nunez, and Heidi Waterhouse. <em>Docs for Developers: An Engineer’s Field Guide to Technical Writing</em>. New York: Apress, 2021.</li>
<li><a href="https://developers.google.com/style/images" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diagrams, figures, and other images | Google developer documentation style guide</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="style guide" term="style guide"/>
        <category label="UI" term="UI"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Form Design]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/forms</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/forms"/>
        <updated>2024-05-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Somewhere in the midst of my struggle to write a help article for a very long data entry form, a lightbulb clicked on in my mind. I already knew that my article would be more concise if the form was divided into sections with labels. For example, instead of directing people to the bottom-left corner of the form, I could direct them to, say, the output section. Why not suggest dividing the form into sections?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Somewhere in the midst of my struggle to write a help article for a very long data entry form, a lightbulb clicked on in my mind. I already knew that my article would be more concise if the form was divided into sections with labels. For example, instead of directing people to the <em>bottom-left corner</em> of the form, I could direct them to, say, the <em>output section</em>. Why not suggest dividing the form into sections?</p>
<p>I decided to submit a feature request! I would propose dividing the form into labeled sections and moving a couple of fields. My colleagues agreed the form is complicated. Dividing it into sections would make it easier to use. But like a good librarian (in my case, a good former librarian), I wanted to provide a rationale with citations.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/forms#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Form design</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="questions">Questions<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/forms#questions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Questions" title="Direct link to Questions">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>What does user research tell us about how to design online forms?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/forms#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>group fields logically</li>
<li>use a one-column layout</li>
<li>place labels above fields, not to the left</li>
<li>use action-based words on buttons</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/forms#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://designlab.com/blog/form-ui-design-best-practices/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A UX/UI Guide to Designing User-Friendly Forms | Designlab</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/videos/better-forms-visual-organization/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Better Forms Through Visual Organization| Nielsen Norman Group</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="UI" term="UI"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trust Equation]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/trust</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/trust"/>
        <updated>2024-05-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Technical communication podcasts funnel my thoughts toward work every morning during my commute. In a Content Strategy podcast that I listened to a few days ago, Kristina Halvorson’s guest Chelsea Larsson referred to something called the Trust Equation. As Larsson described it, the Trust Equation is a framework that illustrates how people assess the trustworthiness of their colleagues. It caught my attention because it validated my approach to work life. I think I have a decent chance of getting a good score!]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Technical communication podcasts funnel my thoughts toward work every morning during my commute. In a <em>Content Strategy</em> podcast that I listened to a few days ago, Kristina Halvorson’s guest Chelsea Larsson referred to something called the Trust Equation. As Larsson described it, the Trust Equation is a framework that illustrates how people assess the trustworthiness of their colleagues. It caught my attention because it validated my approach to work life. I think I have a decent chance of getting a good score!</p>
<p>In the Trust Equation, self-orientation is the denominator. I tend to keep my self-orientation at work fairly low. I prefer learning about colleagues to talking about myself, and showing that I care about other people  makes me feel good.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/trust#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.contentstrategy.com/episodes/episode-42-chelsea-larsson-zendesk-tactics-to-advocate-for-content-design" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ep. 42: Chelsea Larsson, Zendesk | The Content Strategy Podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://trustedadvisor.com/why-trust-matters/understanding-trust/understanding-the-trust-equation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Understanding The Trust Equation | Trusted Advisor.com</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="communication" term="communication"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organize Content Into Sections]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/sections</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/sections"/>
        <updated>2024-04-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few weeks ago, I started working on a help article for a data entry form. The form produces reports that can be used to evaluate profitability, uncover data entry errors, send mass mailings, and more. The form has grown longer over the years, and it now contains more than 30 input fields with no section dividers and no headings. The goal of my article was to define all the fields. This was a thorny information architecture challenge.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I started working on a help article for a data entry form. The form produces reports that can be used to evaluate profitability, uncover data entry errors, send mass mailings, and more. The form has grown longer over the years, and it now contains more than 30 input fields with no section dividers and no headings. The goal of my article was to define all the fields. This was a thorny information architecture challenge.</p>
<p>How would I format the article so that a reader could quickly make sense of the content? If I listed the fields one after the other with no section dividers and no headings, my list would be too long to comprehend. If I divided the list into categories, that would falsely suggest that the form is divided into categories too.</p>
<p>As a writer, I know that separating large blocks of content into chunks makes scanning easier, and as a former educator, I know that organizing content into meaningful categories helps people learn. So, I decided to break my lists into sections based on the order in which the fields appear in the form. Within each section, I would create subsections based on function.</p>
<p>This is an imperfect solution, but it’s the best solution for now. (Separately, I’ll recommend a new organization scheme for the form!) I found a couple of sources to support my decisions.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/sections#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Help article for a long form</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="questions">Questions<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/sections#questions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Questions" title="Direct link to Questions">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Why should large blocks of content be divided into sections?</li>
<li>Why should content be organized into categories?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/sections#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Breaking up large blocks of content into chunks makes scanning easier.</li>
<li>Grouping related content together helps people understand it and remember it.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/sections#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.learningscientists.org/blog/2023/7/6?rq=chunk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sources of Cognitive Load | The Learning Scientists</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/chunking/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How Chunking Helps Content Processing | Nielsen Norman Group</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="info architecture" term="info architecture"/>
        <category label="learning" term="learning"/>
        <category label="online reading" term="online reading"/>
        <category label="UI" term="UI"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ordered and Unordered Lists]]></title>
        <id>https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/lists</id>
        <link href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/lists"/>
        <updated>2024-03-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m creating templates for colleagues to use when they write articles for the internal knowledgebase. This week, I tested my how-to template by comparing it to an older how-to article that was already published. The article was user-friendly in many ways. It focused on a single problem, it opened with an informative scope statement, and it provided plenty of white space.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m creating templates for colleagues to use when they write articles for the internal knowledgebase. This week, I tested my how-to template by comparing it to an older how-to article that was already published. The article was user-friendly in many ways. It focused on a single problem, it opened with an informative scope statement, and it provided plenty of white space.</p>
<p>What my editorial eye zoomed in on was the lower half of the page. The content there was divided into a series of short paragraphs, each only 1 or 2 sentences long. When I read the paragraphs more closely, I realized that many of them were troubleshooting steps.</p>
<p>I concluded that my how-to template should call out the importance of using numbered lists for steps. It will need to explain why numbered lists are helpful to readers.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-im-working-on">What I’m Working On<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/lists#what-im-working-on" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What I’m Working On" title="Direct link to What I’m Working On">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Templates</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="questions">Questions<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/lists#questions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Questions" title="Direct link to Questions">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Why should we use bulleted lists and numbered lists?</li>
<li>Why should long lists be organized and divided into sections with headings?</li>
<li>Why do we need white space?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="answers">Answers<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/lists#answers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Answers" title="Direct link to Answers">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>People don’t read online, they seek</li>
<li>To guide the reader’s attention, ask: Can you break any complicated concepts out into groups of simple items? If the answer is yes, then use numbered (or, <em>ordered</em>) lists for sequential items, and use bulleted (or, <em>unordered</em>) lists for non-sequential items</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="citations">Citations<a href="https://github.io/carriewritesdocs/blog/lists#citations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Citations" title="Direct link to Citations">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/how-people-read-online/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How People Read Online: New and Old Findings | Nielsen Norman Group (2020)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/f-shaped-pattern-reading-web-content/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">F-Shaped Pattern of Reading on the Web: Misunderstood, But Still Relevant (Even on Mobile) | Nielsen Norman Group (2017)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/blah-blah-text-keep-cut-or-kill/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blah-Blah Text: Keep, Cut, or Kill? | Nielsen Norman Group (2007)</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Carrie M. Macfarlane</name>
            <uri>https://www.linkedin.com/in/carrie-m-macfarlane/</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="info architecture" term="info architecture"/>
        <category label="online reading" term="online reading"/>
        <category label="style guide" term="style guide"/>
        <category label="templates" term="templates"/>
    </entry>
</feed>